Guide to the Miscellaneous Parliamentary Manuscripts
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
[Miscellaneous Parliamentary manuscripts]
1601-1700
OSBORN FB158
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.17
(1 volume)
Volume, in multiple hands, of seven booklets primarily on such topics as law, Parliament, government, and public finances. Parliamentary items include speeches by Thomas Wentworth, earl of Strafford, and Francis Seymour, Baron Trowbridge, complaining about forced loans, billeting of soldiers, and other grievances; a copy of the Spanish ambassador's complaints against George Villiers, Duke of Buckingham, as well as his own excuses for the conduct of the Spanish during marriage negotiations between Charles I and the Infanta Maria; a Parliamentary grievance against Buckingham; and journal notes for the House of Lords in 1621.
Browne, John, approximately 1608-1691
Immediate Source of Acquisition
For provenance information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The following finding aid is a complete inventory of the contents of Osborn fb158. This list was reformatted from previously existing cataloging.
Law -- Great Britain; Nobility -- Great Britain; Great Britain -- Foreign relations -- Spain; Great Britain -- Politics and government -- 1603-1649; Spain -- Foreign relations -- Great Britain; Commonplace books; Charles, King of England, I, 1600-1649; Ashe, Thomas, active 1600-1618; Browne, John, approximately 1608-1691; Buckingham, George Villiers, Duke of, 1592-1628; Strafford, Thomas Wentworth, Earl of, 1593-1641; Great Britain. Parliament; Braye, Alfred Verney-Cave, Baron, 1849-1928 -- Bookplate
- Osborn fb158
  - ASHE, THOMAS, FL.1600-1618
    - "A Briefe Collection of all generall Penall Statutes now in force...", [c.1607] (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      32 p.
      Autograph MS.
      The statutes are arranged under
      general hearings, with a brief
      explanation accompanying. Signature
      of John Browne appears on first page.
      f.I.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [Speech delivered at the opening of Parliament, 1627/8 Mar 17], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      2 p.
      Contemporary MS copy.
      Requests supply for defense of realm
      and expresses willingness to forget
      distractions of the last Parliament.
      Rushworth, v.i, p.476-477.
      f.IIa
  - SEYMOUR, FRANCIS SEYMOUR, BARON TOWBRIDGE, 1590?-1664
    - [Speech in Parliament, 1627/8 March 22], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      1 p.
      Demands redress of grievances before
      supply granted; grievances include
      forced loan, billeting of soldiers,
      imprisonment of gentlemen, etc.
      Rushworth, i, p.499-500.
      f.IIb
  - STRAFFORD, THOMAS WENTWORTH, 1ST EARL OF, 1593-1641
    - [Speech in Parliament, 1627/8 March 22], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Speaks against forced loans and other
      grievances.
      Rushworth, vii, 500-501.
      f.IIc.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [Propositions sent to the House of Commons by the King concerning supply, 1628 Mar 26], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Rushworth, i, 513.
      f.IId.
  - ROUS, FRANCIS, 1579-1659
    - [Speech in Parliament, 1628/9 Jan 26], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      4 p.
      Warns against threats to true
      religion, especially Arminianism.
      Rushworth, i, 645-646.
      f.IIe.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1626. HOUSE OF COMMONS.
    - [Declaration to the Lords, 1626 Mar 8 or 9], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Concerning having George Villiers,
      1st duke of Buckingham (1592-1628)
      committed to custody.
      Rushworth, i, 357-358.
      f.IIf.
  - ELIOT, SIR JOHN, 1592-1632
    - [Speech in Parliament, 1628 June 3], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      14 p.
      Eliot's speech in response to Charles
      I's first answer to the Petition of
      Right.
      Rushworth, i, 591-592.
      f.IIg.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1628. HOUSE OF COMMONS.
    - [Remonstrance of the Commons to the King against the duke of Buckingham, 1628 June], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      17 p.
      Concerns grievances and evils which
      are attributed to the excessive power
      of George Villiers, 1st duke of
      Buckingham (1592-1628).
      f.IIh.
  - [SPANISH AMBASSADOR]
    - [Petition to James I against the Duke of Buckingham, 1624], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Complaints of the duke's all-
      encompassing power, and excuses for
      the conduct of the Spanish during
      marriage negotiations.
      Rushworth, i, 145.
      f.IIi.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1621. HOUSE OF COMMONS.
    - [Debate on foreign affairs, Spain, and the Palatine, and religion. 1621 Nov] (Box 1)
      Includes a purported letter from Pope
      Gregorius XV (1554-1623) to Louis
      XIII, King of France (1601-1643).
      CJ, I, 644-647.
      f.IIj.
  - BROWNE, JOHN, D.1691
    - "A Catalogue of the Nobility of England according to their creations" (Box 1)
      [1625 or later]
      6 p.
      Lists creations from reign of Henry
      II to 1625.
      f.IIIa.
  - BROWNE, JOHN, D.1691
    - [Receipt for payment of annuity, 1640 June 5], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Money received by John Browne for the
      fee of his office from Sir Richard
      Younge, Clerke of the Hanaper in the
      Chancery, bart., d.1651?
      f.IIIa
  - [ANONYMOUS]
    - [Oath of the Clerk of Parliament], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      MS copy in the hand of John Browne.
      17th century.
      f.IIIb.
  - BROWNE, JOHN, D.1691
    - [Memorandum on trade, 17th century] (Box 1)
      3 p.
      Apparently notes from a speech in
      Parliament. A list of reasons for the
      decline in trade and suggestions for
      its recovery.
      f.IIIc.
  - [ANONYMOUS]
    - [Homages of the Spiritual and Temporal Peers at the Coronation of the King, 17th century] (Box 1)
      Two oaths, one for bishops and one
      for lay peers.
  - COTTON, SIR ROBERT BRUCE, BART., 1571-1631
    - "Certaine ge[ner]all rules collected concerning Money and Bullion out of the late consultacon at Cort by Sr Robert Cotton Kt and Barronett and delivered to his Maty at the Bords, 1626" (Box 1)
      5 p.
      Contemporary MS copy, incomplete.
      f.IIId.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1621. HOUSE OF LORDS.
    - [Journal notes for 1621 March-May], [n.d.] (Box 1)
    - 120 p. (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS. Memorandum of
      business, including two speeches by
      the King and Accounts of the trials
      of Sir Giles Mompesson (1584-1651?),
      Sir Henry Yelverton (1566-1629), and
      Francis Bacon, Viscount St Albans
      (1561-1626).
      f.IIIe.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [Questions of the King on points of constitutional law and replies of the judges, c.1628] (Box 1)
      8 p.
      Contemporary MS copy in the hand of
      John Browne. Includes the three
      questions on habeas corpus put to the
      judges 27-31 May 1628, and concerns
      parliamentary privileges from 25
      April 1629. Also an opinion of
      scutage.
      f.IIIf.
  - [ANONYMOUS]
    - "Reasons humbly offered to the Duke of Albemarle, against his going Governour of Jamaica" [c.1687], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      MS. Points out the great expense of
      the office and how little Christopher
      Monck, 2nd duke of Albemarle
      (1653-1688) can afford it.
      f.IV.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF LORDS.
    - [Fees payable to the Clerk of Parliament by the Lords, 17th century], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Includes a sale of fees due to
      various clerks by the Lords,
      depending on the title of the peer.
      Also fees for services.
      f.V.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1646.
    - "A Declaration of the Lords and Comons in Answer to the Scotch Papers" (Box 1)
      [1646 Nov 28]
      62 p.
      Maintains the sole rights of England
      to dispose of the person of the King.
      Rushworth, vi, 341-372.
      f.VI.
  - [ELSYNGE, HENRY, 1598-1654]
    - "Modus tenendi Parliamentum apud Anglos" (Box 1)
      [c.1625]
      120 p.
      Contemporary MS copy in English.
      Contains only Chapter 1 of the first
      book. Book 1 was published in 1663
      with the title: The Ancient and
      Present Manner of holding Parliaments
      in England.
      f.VII.